Francesco Rota

Data Scientist & Quantitative Ecologist, PhD

✓ rotafran@outlook.com
 ✓ +41 765199312
 ✓ Zürich, Switzerland

in linkedin.com/in/francescorota93 Personal Website

Summary

Quantitative ecologist with 7+ years of experience in spatial modeling, biodiversity monitoring, GIS, and data science. Passionate about ecological forecasting, forest ecosystems, and applying AI to conservation. PhD in Mountain Environment and Agriculture.

Technical Skills

• **Programming:** R, Python, SQL, Bash • **Tools:** Git, Docker, Slurm (HPC), Shiny, LaTeX, HTML

• Geospatial: QGIS, ArcGIS, Google Earth Engine

• **Data Sources:** Remote Sensing, Field Sampling, • **Modeling:** Machine Learning, Statistics,

Species Distribution Models

Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher

WSL, Birmensdorf, Switzerland (2022–2024)

Modelled forest biodiversity patterns using high-res soil maps. Developed SDMs, R workflows, and handled HPC computation.

Visiting Researcher

University of Innsbruck (2020–2021)

Studied population genomics of alpine plants. Managed bioinformatics pipelines and RADseq data analysis.

Researcher & Teaching Assistant

Free University of Bozen (2018–2022)

Worked on climate change impacts on endemic flora. Taught courses on GIS, statistics, and ecology.

Education

PhD in Mountain Environment & Agriculture

MSc in Natural Sciences

UNIBZ, 2018–2022

University of Bologna, 2015–2017

BSc in Natural Sciences

University of Milan, 2012–2015

Selected Projects

SOLID (WSL): SDMs for plants and fungi using novel soil data.

DOLE (UNIBZ): Phylogeography of Dolomites endemic plants.

Laboratorio di Scienze: Science outreach for kids (Project Manager).

Languages Interests

Italian (Native), English (C1), Spanish (C1), Photography, mountaineering, speleology German (B1), French (B1) Driving Licence A + B

Certifications

Computer Science for Artificial Intelligence – HarvardX, Harvard University 2024 Professional Habilitation - Albo degli Agrotecnici e Agrotecnici Laureati, Italy, 2022

Publications

Peer-reviewed articles in *Journal of Biogeography, Science of the Total Environment, Molecular Ecology, Scientific Reports.* Full list: Google Scholar Profile